Guide to the Papers of Elizabeth Strauss Plaut (1910-2003) 1738-2006 AR 25309 / MF 932
Center for Jewish History, Publisher.
- Series IV: Oversized Family Trees, undated; 1 OS box.
  Series IV includes several oversized family trees originally separated from the rest of the collection. The series holds seven rolled family trees related to the Strauss side of the family, with Abraham, Dreyfoos, and Strauss family members listed, among others. Two trees relating to the Plaut side of the family are also part of this series.
  - Strauss Family Trees (Rolled), undated (Box OS 128)
  - Plaut Family Trees, undated (Box OS 128)
- Series V: Writing and Publishing, 1977-1998; 0.5 linear foot.
  Series V holds files pertaining to the publication of Elizabeth Strauss Plaut's books and articles, originally found together, primarily in untitled folders. This series includes unpublished manuscripts of texts and family trees, along with correspondence with publishers. Among the manuscripts are both unpublished texts for two of Elizabeth Strauss Plaut's books, as well as copies of shorter articles on genealogical research, some of which were published in the journals Search and Toledot.
  A few files pertaining to the publication of The Guggenheim/ Wormser Family: a Genealogical 300-Year Memoir and The Gumprichs of Münster/ Westphalia: a Tale of Four Continents, originally found among the other papers pertaining to their respective families, have been left with the papers of the subseries in which they were originally located.
  - Genealogical Numbers Game - Article, 1990s (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Family Trees, 1990s? (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Family Trees - from Aldingen, Wuerttemberg, Worms, 1990s? (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Loose Pages - Dispersion of the Family, 1996? (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Loose Pages and Family Trees, 1990s (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Manuscript Draft - Index, 1990s? (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Manuscript Draft - Pages 1-125 - With Revisions, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Manuscript Draft - Unpaginated - With Revisions, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Manuscript Draft - Wormser Stories Second Copy - Pages 4-125 With Gaps, 1990s (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Guggenheim/ Wormser Family - Revised Pages Proofs with Corrections, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Gumprichs of Muenster/ Westphalia - Manuscript Draft and Family Trees, 1990s? (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Gumprichs of Muenster/ Westphalia - Manuscript Drafts - Family Trees and Text Excerpts, 1990s? (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Gumprichs of Muenster/ Westphalia - Publishing Correspondence, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - KTAV Publishing Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - KTAV Publishing Correspondence - Guggenheim/Wormser Book, 1995-1997 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - KTAV Publishing Correspondence - Guggenheim/ Wormser Book - Announcements, Reactions, Reviews, 1996-1998 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Only You Can Do It - Article, 1988-1990s (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - Search Magazine - Correspondence, 1985-1991 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Therese Abraham Strauss - Biographical Article, 1990s? (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Toledot Journal - Correspondence and Articles, 1977-1981 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Written in Stone - Article, 1987-1993 (Box 13, Folder 31)
- Series VI: Visual Material, 1865-1999; 0.625 linear foot.
  Series VI contains photographs, photocopies of photographs, and a few negatives portraying family members from both Plaut and Strauss sides of the family, as well as invitations and announcements of family events and an unidentified drawing. Most of these papers were found together in untitled folders; most other photographs and photocopies of photographs in this collection have remained among the correspondence and other papers where they were originally filed.
  A large, untitled folder with some correspondence, photographs, and notes was divided during processing by family or document format. A few clippings from publications or newspapers featuring photos of family members have also been included in this series. Among the photographs of members of the Kline family is a childhood photograph presumably of the actor, Kevin Kline.
  Box 15 holds numerous family photographs. These primarily depict individuals and groups of individuals, many of whom are mentioned elsewhere in the collection. Families represented here include the Gumprichs, Hillers, Dreyfooses, Plauts, Pappenheimers, and Strausses.
  - Abraham, Nathan, and Wormser Families - Photograph Copies and Notes, undated, 1865-1919 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Apt Family, 1994-1995 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Clippings, 1937, 1974-1977 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence with Photographs - Gumprich Family, 1916-1999 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence with Photographs - Other Family Members, 1917-1996 (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence with Photographs - Other Papers - Notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence with Photographs - W. Gunther and Elizabeth Strauss Plaut, 1983-1987 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence with Photographs - Wisebart and Cahn Families, 1881-1984 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Drawing, undated (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Elsass Family - Carolina Elsass, 1800s? (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - Invitations and Announcements, 1895-1920 (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Negatives - Plaut Family Members, undated, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - Oversized Photograph - Unidentified Group, undated (Box OS 128)
  - Photographs, 1915-1991 (Box 15)
  - Photographs - Kline Family, 1951?-1983 (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - Photographs - Myers Family, 1976, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 45)
  - Wormser Family, undated, 1926 (Box 13, Folder 46)
- Series VII: Non-Genealogical Papers, 1940s-2001; 0.625 linear foot.
  Divided in the following manner:
  Subseries 1: Writing, Correspondence, and Notes
  Subseries 2: Collected Material
  Series VII is comprised of papers that do not relate to Elizabeth Straus Plaut's genealogical research. Among the papers found here is a small amount of correspondence, writing, and notes as well as collected papers such as articles and stamps.
  - Subseries 1: Writings, Correspondence, and Notes, 1940s-2001; 0.375 linear foot.
    Subseries 1 holds non-genealogical papers created by Elizabeth Strauss Plaut or her husband, Rabbi W. Gunther Plaut. Included here are a small amount of personal correspondence, notes, and drafts of lectures and public addresses, short stories, and a play.
    Among the papers of this series is one folder of personal correspondence holding five letters sent from Elizabeth Strauss Plaut to her husband during World War II. Other correspondence includes a folder of letters and notes of W. Gunther Plaut, most of which relate to his duties as Rabbi.
    Several folders in this series include scripts or notes used for lectures and public addresses. These include the text of a lecture given at a meeting of the National Association of Retired Reform Rabbis (NAORRR) and several folders of notes used by Elizabeth Plaut in invocations for Mount Zion and Holy Temple Sisterhood events, as well as for the installation of organizational officers. This subseries also contains the text of a sermon given on Yom Kippur Eve in 1978, perhaps by W. Gunther Plaut.
    Elizabeth Strauss Plaut's creative writing is additionally evidenced in Subseries 1. Found among the papers of this subseries are a short story "Both House and Machine" written by her and her brother William Strauss as well as scripts for the play "The Road Back." Other related papers include correspondence with the publishers of World Over regarding the publication of her short stories as well as an advertisement for the children's game created by Elizabeth Plaut "Holiplay."
    - Correspondence - Personal - Elizabeth Strauss Plaut to W. Gunther Plaut, 1940s? (Box 13, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence - World Over Magazine, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence and Notes - W. Gunther Plaut, 1973-1976, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 49)
    - Holiplay Advertisement, undated (Box 13, Folder 50)
    - National Association of Retired Reform Rabbis - Lecture, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 51)
    - Notecards and Notebook - Central and South American Mythology, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Notes - Unidentified, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Scripts - Organizations - Meetings and Officer Installations, undated, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Scripts - Organizations - Meetings and Officer Installations - Invocations - Holy Blossom Temple Sisterhood, 1949-1971 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Scripts - Organizations - Meetings and Officer Installations - Invocations - Mount Zion Temple Sisterhood, 1948-1961 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Scripts - Plays, undated, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Short Story - Both House and Machine, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Yom Kippur Address, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Collected Material, 1969-1998; 0.25 linear foot.
    This small subseries is comprised of material collected by Elizabeth Plaut that does not appear to relate to her genealogical research. Most prominent in this subseries are several folders of Isreali stamps and correspondence with the Israeli Postal Authority Philatelic Services regarding the purchase of Israeli stamps. Other papers found here include two music programs and a few folders of accumulated articles, most relating to scientific or health topics.
    - Articles - Humor, 1990s? (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Articles - Scientific and Medical, 1985-1997 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Articles by Maxine Haberman, 1983-1989 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Music Programs, 1969, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Stamp Collecting - Israel Postal Authority Philatelic Services - Advertisements, 1994-1996 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Stamp Collecting - Israel Postal Authority Philatelic Services -Correspondence and Receipts, 1995-1996 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Stamp Collecting - Stamps, 1983-1998 (Box 14, Folder 15)